Guide to the Barnard-Talcott Hollerith Family Papers, 1790-1858 MS2088
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Barnard-Talcott Hollerith Family Papers
1790-1981
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Barnard-Talcott Hollerith family
MS2088
1 Linear Feet
Collection contains account books and notes that belonged to the Barnard-Talcott family in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries in England the the United States. Materials date from 1790 to 1858. The collection also includes tapes and transcripts of oral histories conducted with Virginia and Nan Hollerith in 1981.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Virginia and Ann Hollerith, whose great-grandfather Robert Barnard immigrated to the United States around 1820, donated these items to The George Washington University in February 1976 along with 237 printed volumes.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Barnard-Talcott family originated in America about 1820, when Robert Barnard (1786-1852) arrived from England and settled in Washington, D.C. He built a home in Georgetown Heights he named Normanstone after the school he had attended in England. His granddaughter, Lucia Beverly Talcott, was married in 1890 to Herman Hollerith, engineer and inventor of the punch card system. Talcott and Hollerith's daughters, Virginia and Nan, gathered this collection of family material.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains account books and notes that belonged to the Barnard-Talcott family in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries in England the the United States. Materials date from 1790 to 1858.
The collection also includes tapes and transcripts of oral histories conducted with Virginia and Nann Hollerith in 1981. These capture their recollections of eight decades of life in Washington, D.C.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Account books, Research notes, Miscellaneous, and Oral history.
United States; Great Britain; England; Oral history; Normanstone (Washington, D.C.); Hollerith, Virginia; Hollerith, Nannie Talcott; Hollerith, Lucia Beverly Talcott; Hollerith, Herman; Barnard, Robert
- Account books, 1790-1858; MS2088 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains account books kept by the Barnard family in England and the United States from 1790 to 1858.
  - Account book possibly belonging to Samuel Barnard, 1790-1791 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account book possibly belonging to Samuel Barnard, 1791-1794 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Account book by the Executors of the late S. Barnard, 1810-1814 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Account book belonging to a William Barnard in England, 1815-1818 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Account book belonging to William Barnard in England, 1817-1820 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account book belonging to William Barnard in England, 1820-1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account book and diary possibly written by a Norwich cousin of William Barnard, 1821-1832 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Account book of one of the Boston (England) Barnards, 1823-1826 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Account book possibly belonging to one of the Boston (England) Barnards, 1825-1835 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Account book in English money and with some of the same surnames mentioned as are in the identified Barnard account books, 1835-1843 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Account book in American money and by Robert W. Barnard, possibly a son of the Robert Barnard (d.1852) who left England for Washington, 1852-1853 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Account book belonging to T.M.R. Talcott. Thomas Mann Randolph Talcott's brother Charles Gratiot married a Barnard in 1858, 1857-1858 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Research notes, 1805-1806; MS2088 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains notes kept by John James Barnard while attending the Normanstone School in England in 1805-06.
  - Notes on Joseph Priestley's Lectures on histor by John James Barnard while attending Normanstone School in England, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Adam Smith's Wealth of Nations by John James Barnard while attending Normanstone School in England, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous, undated; MS2088 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains sheets of calculations, including annuity figures, found in R. Barnard's copy of Moivre's "Doctrine of Chances."
  - Sheets of calculations (including annuity figures) found in the R. Barnard copy of Moivre's Doctrine of Chances, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Oral history, 1981; MS2088 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains an oral history, in both audiotapes and a complete transcription, photographs and negatives. The oral history was conducted in 1981. The oral history was conducted with Virginia Hollerith and Nan Hollerith. They were the daughters of Herman Hollerith an inventor of the punched card and founder of the Tabulating Machine Company later called IBM. The oral history chiefly concerns family recollections of the Hollerith, Barnard, and Talcott families and childhood memories of life in suburban Maryland and Georgetown before 1920. The images and negatives are family images of people and houses.
  - Oral history audiotapes, 13 tapes, undated (Box SHARED Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Oral history, 04/27/1981-04/29/1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oral history, 04/30/1981-05/01/1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)